Guide to the Latino/a Studies in the Global South Records, 2001-2016 UA.25.44.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Latino/a Studies in the Global South Records
2001-2016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Latino/a Studies in the Global South
UA.25.44.0001
.75 Linear Feet
The Latino/a Studies in the Global South program at Duke University was formally created in 2008. The program offers an undergraduate certificate and promotes interdisciplinary research, teaching, and study related to Latino and Latina communities, particularly in the U.S. South and the Global South. The Latino/a Studies in the Global South Records include the files of the Executive Director of the program from 2008-2016.
Biographical / Historical
In Fall 1997, The Concilio Latino/Hispano/Americano, with approximately sixty faculty, student, and staff members, formed to foster a Latino intellectual community at Duke University and to develop a U.S. Latino agenda for the campus. The Concilio organized its work around three themes that were addressed by separate subcommittees: research and academics; student and campus life; and community outreach. A main goal of the academic subcommittee and the Concilio as a whole was to establish a program in Latino Studies at Duke University.
By Spring 2001, the first Latino Studies cluster was taught. Furthermore, a committee composed of Duke faculty, students, and staff members submitted a proposal for a certificate program in Latino Studies, with support requested for a director, conference, faculty course development awards and administrative costs. The committee received partial funding, which was used to support the development of three additional courses and program administration.
In Fall 2004, a new "Latino/a Studies Initiative at Duke" was set forth for the academic year; included in the plans were a welcome reception and organizational meeting, several lecture discussions with invited speakers, two film and director events, and research support awards for undergraduates, graduates, and faculty members.
In Spring 2008, The University approved the undergraduate certificate, "Latino/a Studies in the Global South,” with Jenny Snead Williams as the Executive Director and with Professor Antonio Viego as the Faculty Director. In Fall 2008, the certificate’s “program” status was approved by the university. For a more in depth timeline of the Program’s significant events, please consult the program’s “History” page at http://latinostudies.duke.edu/about/history.
Access Restrictions
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Use of audiotapes and videotapes from this collection requires the creation of reference copies. Reference copies for some materials may have been made, and if a reference copy exists, it is noted in this finding aid. To arrange for the creation of reference copies of other items, please contact University Archives staff. Although these recordings are now stored in a stable environment, their condition and playback quality is unknown.
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use these records.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Latino/a Studies in the Global South Records were received by the Duke Univesity Archives as a transfer in 2017.
Related Materials
Mi Gente Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Trinity College of Arts and Sciences, Office of the Dean Records, Duke University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Collection Overview
Collection contains the office files of the Executive Director of the Program in Latino/a Studies in the Global South from 2008-2016, Jenny Snead Williams. Materials and topics include flyers for courses taught under the Program’s instructors; proposals for the program’s certificate status; budgets; information about art exhibits, conferences, scholarly lectures, and readings sponsored or co-sponsored by the program; information concerning similar programs; and printed material related to similar programs at other institutions. A DVD documenting publicity of the Malaquias Montoya exhibit is present in the corresponding folder. Two VHS cassette tapes are present documenting the 2003 Seeds of Change: Latino/a Citizenship(s) in the Here and Now conference. The materials date from 2001-2016.
Latin Americans -- United States; Latin American students; Duke University. Latino/a Studies in the Global South; Montoya, Malaquias,, 1938-
- Materials related to courses and curriculum (syllabi, proposals, descriptions), 2001-2008, undated (Box 1)
- Latino/a Studies, other programs, 2005-2008 (Box 1)
- Exhibits, other, 2009, undated (Box 1)
- Pedro Lasch, 2006-2009 (Box 1)
- Antonio Viego, 2008 (Box 1)
- Junot Diaz visit, 2009 (Box 1)
- Exhibit, Malaquias Montoya, 2009 (Box 1)
- Montoya: DP Publicity, 2009 (Box 2, Optical-disc UA25440001-OP-0001)
- Materials related to Conferences/Symposia, 2002-2010 (Box 1)
- Program's brochures, handouts, and website templates, 2006-2010 (Box 1)
- Film, Angelica's Dreams, 2010 (Box 1)
- Promotional materials related to courses, 2008-2015, undated (Box 1)
- Lectures, programming, 2005-2015 (Box 1)
- Patricia Engel, signed promotional material, 2016 (Box 1)
- Notes from Program's events, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted until 2031.
- Program's History, proposals, structure of program, 2005-2007 (Box 1)
  Restricted until 2032.
- Meeting Notes, 2005, undated (Box 1)
  Restricted until 2030.
- Jose D. Saldivar, 2006-2007 (Box 1)
- Student Engagement, 2003-2008 (Box 1)
  Restricted until 2033.
- Miscellaneous email correspondence, 2005-2008 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous items, undated (Box 1)
- Budget requests, job notes, 2005-2009 (Box 1)
  Restricted until 2034.
- Events, Programming, 2006-2010 (Box 1)
  Restricted until 2035.
- Seeds of Change: Latino/a Citizenship(s) in the Here and Now, February 14-15, 2003; 2 VHS (Box 2, Video-cassette UA25440001-VHS-0001, UA25440001-VHS-0002)